<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="introduction">
    <?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>

    <chapterinfo>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>JBoss Developer Studio</keyword>
            <keyword>Eclipse</keyword>
            <keyword>Java</keyword>
            <keyword>JBoss</keyword>
            <keyword>JBoss Tools</keyword>
            <keyword>JBDS</keyword>
            <keyword>ESB</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </chapterinfo>

    <title>Introduction</title>
    
    <section>
        
        <title>What is ESB?</title>
        
        <para>ESB (Enterprise Service Bus) - an abstraction layer on top of an implementation of an enterprise messaging system
            that provides the features with which Service Oriented Architectures may be implemented.</para>
            
        <para>The ESB is seen as the next generation of EAI – better and without the vendor-lockin characteristics of old.
            As such, many of the capabilities of a good ESB mirror those of existing EAI offerings. Traditional EAI stacks consist of:
            Business Process Monitoring, Integrated Development Environment, Human Workflow User Interface, Business Process Management,
            Connectors, Transaction Manager, Security, Application Container, Messaging Service, Metadata Repository, Naming and Directory Service,
            Distributed Computing Architecture.</para>
            
            <para>As with EAI systems, ESB is not about business logic – that is left to higher levels.
                It is about infrastructure logic. Although there are many different definitions of what constitutes an ESB,
                what everyone agrees on now is that an ESB is part of an SOA infrastructure. However,
                SOA is not simply a technology or a product: it's a style of design, with many aspects
                (such as architectural, methodological and organisational) unrelated to the actual technology.
                But obviously at some point it becomes necessary to map the abstract SOA to a concrete
                implementation and that's where the ESB comes in to play.</para>

    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Other relevant resources on the topic</title>
        
        <para>You can find a set of benefits and other extra information on:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/jbossesb">JBoss ESB</ulink></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><ulink url="http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/JBossESB">JBoss Wiki</ulink></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/jbossesb/docs/index.html">JBoss ESB Documentation Library</ulink></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    
    </section>
    
</chapter>
